Guide to the Daniel Bell Research Files on U.S. Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement TAM.080
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: The Communist Party U.S.A. and the American Labor Movement: Individual Labor Unions
  - Subseries II:D: Cloth, Hat, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
    - Trade Union Educational League Materials re: CHCMWIU, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Trade Union Educational League Materials re: CHCMWIU, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Yiddish Language Materials re: CHCMWIU, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II:E: Joint Board of Cloak, Skirt, Dress and Reefer Makers Unions of N.Y. (ILGWU) & Needle Trades Workers Industrial Union
    - Dubinsky / Stolberg - Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Index Card Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Needle Trades / NTWIU - Internal Documents, Memos, Reports By/About NTWIU, CPUSA Role, 1925 Expulsions, Industry Conditions, undated, 1925-1926 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Needle Trades Workers Industrial Union Conventions, 1929-1932 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - NTWIU Youth Section, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II:F: Miscellaneous Unions
    - Amalgamated Food Workers Union - Notes for 1920-1940 Period, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Bridges, Harry (Longshore), 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Fur Workers (Includes Furriers' Bulletin, Oct 1933), 1927, 1933, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - International Ladies Garment Workers Union. Cutters Local 10 - Propaganda from Three-Cornered Leadership Struggle, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - National Maritime Union, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Pacific Maritime Assn: Longshore Wage Review; Hourly Wage & Fringe Costs, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Packinghouse Workers Union (Includes: "Early Unionism in Packing…1840 to 1933"), 1947-1949 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Passaic Textile Strike, 1926 - Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Rubber Workers, 1948-1955 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Transport Workers Union / Michael Quill - Clippings, 1948, 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - United Auto Workers / Walter Reuther - Clips, Reports, Statements re Struggle with Communist Party, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - United Public Workers Expulsion from CIO [ts of CIO Hearings, 150 pp], Jan 1950 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Upholsterers' International Union / Salvatore B. Hoffman (President), undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series III: American Labor Unions and Industrial Relations
  This section consists of both general studies of the labor movement and information pertaining to specific unions.
  - Subseries III:A: General studies of the labor movement
    The general studies include articles, reports, and book reviews arranged topically under the headings: union leadership, union structure, labor and economic conditions, union membership and organizing drives, industrial relations, labor ideology, labor and government, and foreign unions.
    - Bibliographies - Labor, Industrial Relations, undated, 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Conflict and Cooperation in Industry ( Journal of Social Issues, 2:1), Feb 1946 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Industrial Relations: Collective Bargaining, 1938, 1940, 1949-1955 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Industrial Relations: Determinants of Strikes, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Industrial Relations: Jurisdictional Disputes, undated, 1946-1955 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Industrial Relations: Pensions, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 5A)
    - Industrial Relations: Unions in Public Service, 1946-1955 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Industrial Relations: Work Rules, Industrial Factors, Psychological Influences, 1950-1963 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Labor and Economic Conditions - Industry, 1946-1963 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Labor Economics - Agriculture, 1938-1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Labor Economics - Effect of Unions on Wages, undated, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Labor Economics - Trends and Conditions in Industry, 1942-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Labor Ideology, 1947-1955 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Labor Leadership - General, 1944-1955 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Non-U.S. Labor Unions, undated, 1938-1957 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Union Membership and Labor Monopoly, 1944-1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Union Membership and Organization, 1944, 1950-1956 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Union Structure: Democracy & Bureaucracy; A Force in Community, 1943-1960 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III:B: Labor and Government (articles, news reports, pamphlets, etc.)
    - Government Labor Regulation - Railroad Unions, 1939-1954 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Government Policy Toward Labor 1930s-1950s, 1939-1957 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Labor at 1952 [Democratic] Convention, 1940-1952 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Labor - Postwar Planning, 1943-1948 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Labor Representation in Government, 1944-1954 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - National Labor Relations Board, 1939-1954 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - National War Labor Board, 1943-1944 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Secretaries of Labor: Martin Durkin, James P. Mitchell, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Wage Stabilization Board, 1946-1952 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Subseries III:C: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen
    The material specifically devoted to the Teamsters provides a substantial introduction to the recent history of the union. It includes biographical studies of Dan Tobin, Dave Beck, and James Hoffa, articles on Teamster history and structure and news reports concerning Teamster relations with other unions. Almost half the material deals with the charges of racketeering made against union officials during the 1950's. These files are composed primarily of articles and news reports but also include the Report of the AFL CIO Ethical Practices Committee to the AFL CIO Executive Council re: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, September 16, 1957, and the Proceedings of the Seventeenth Convention of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, September 1957.
    - Beck, Dave, 1948-1955 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Hoffa, James, 1953-1957 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Racketeering Charges (1957-58), 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Racketeering Charges (1957-58) News Reports (1), 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Racketeering Charges (1957-58) News Reports (2), 1957-1958 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Racketeering; Intra-Union Disputes (1953-54), 1953-1954 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Structure and Expansion, 1948-1953 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Tobin, Dan, 1947-1952 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III:D: United Auto Workers
    The United Auto Workers material also heavily emphasizes the post War period. There are biographical sketches of important union officials, notes on the history of the union, and articles concerning the important question of internal democracy. Much of the material concerns the industrial relations of the United Auto Workers: strikes, negotiations, and innovations such as the Guaranteed Annual Wage.
    - History, 1936-1956 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Industrial Relations: Chrysler Dispute, 1950, 1948-1955 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Industrial Relations: GM Dispute, 1945-46; Boeing Aircraft, 1945; Ford, 1949; GM Formula, 1948; UAW in Toledo, 1949 & Richard Gasser, 1945-1958 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Reuther, Walter - Biographical, 1945-1958 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Reuther, Walter - Policies, 1946-1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Toledo, Ohio, 1949-1950 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - UAW Conventions - News Clippings, 1949-1953 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III:E: International Ladies Garment Workers Union (articles & news reports)
    The International Ladies' Garment Workers Union and United Mine Workers Union files consist of biographical studies of the unions' leaders and articles concerning their history, structure, and industrial relations. Together with these files there are miscellaneous articles and news clippings on the Pulp, Sulphite, and Paper Mill Workers Union; the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners; and the Textile Workers Union of America.
    - Dubinsky, History, Industrial Relations, Structure, 1934-1949 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Subseries III:F: United Mineworkers of America (articles & news reports)
    - History; John L. Lewis, 1939-1954 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Leaders' Bios: Thomas Kennedy, John L. Lewis, John Owens, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Subseries III:G: Miscellaneous Articles and News Clippings on Other Unions
    This subseries contains selections from the convention proceedings of the Federation of Trades and Labor Unions and the American Federation of Labor showing the list of delegates to the conventions, together with notes on the elections at the national conventions of the AFL for the period of 1886-1905.
    - Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters: book review by DB, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Entertainment Industry Unions, 1949, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - International Association of Machinists, 1949-1952 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite & Paper Mill Workers Journal, volume 36, number1.Contents: "Fifty Years of Trade Unionism in Berlin, New Hampshire," by H.W. Sullivan, Jan 1952-Feb 1952 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Textile Workers Union of America, undated, 1948-1952 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - United Brotherhood of Carpenters, 1949-1953 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Olander, Victor A. Confidential Report to Matthew Woll (re Newspaper Guild), Oct 19, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Subseries III:H: A.F.L. C.I.O. (articles, clippings, notes)
    This subseries includes biographical studies of George Meany, Phil Murray, Alan Haywood, and Sidney Hillman, together with articles and pamphlets concerning the history of the CIO and the AFL CIO merger.
    - AFL, 1939-1958 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - CIO Formation: Pamphlets, Articles, 1930-1952 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - CIO Leaders: Clinton S. Golden, Sidney Hillman, Allen Maywood, undated, 1951-1953 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - CIO Postwar Planning, Political & Economic: Pamphlets, undated, 1943-1948 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Corruption, Role of Charters, undated, 1952-1956 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Merger Negotiations, 1953-1958 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Merger Negotiations: Photographs, 1955-1956 (Box A006, Folder 2)
    - Murry, Phil: Biographical, 1946-1952 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Waterfront Racketeering, 1948-1951 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Waterfront Racketeering: Photograph, 1948 (Box A006, Folder 3)
- Series IV: The American Socialist Party
  The section of the collection devoted to the Socialist Party heavily emphasizes the 1930s.
  - Subseries IV:A: The Socialist Party before World War I
    For the period before World War I there is some Connecticut SP material; minutes of the State Convention at New Haven, 1906; state constitutions of 1906 and 1909; letters, platforms, and bulletins concerning the elections of 1906, 1910, 1912, and 1913; and newspaper clippings concerning the Socialists in office.
    - Connecticut SP Documents.Contents: Minutes of the convention at New Haven, 1906; constitutions, 1906 and 1909; election material: letter of nomination and acceptance letter of E. D. Hall for SP nomination for Governor, 1906; state SP platforms of 1906, 1912, 1913; sample ballots for 1910, 1912; party bulletins and resolutions; clippings concerning the SP in office, 1906-1913 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - O'Sheel, Shaemas: Letter to Daniel Bell, re Socialist Party in NYC, Early 20th Century, Aug 25, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Socialism in America: Articles by Earl Browder, Maurice Goldbloom, Norman Thomas, Will Herberg, Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr., James Weinstein, 1950s-1960s (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV:B: The Socialist Party: 1920s
    For the 1920's there are news clippings concerning relations between the Socialist Party and the Conference for Progressive Political Action; miscellaneous National Convention Papers for 1924 and 1928; and the Twenty first Anniversary Convention Book, Cuyahoga County, Ohio, 1922.
    - Cuyahoga County Local Socialist Party: 21st Anniversary Convention Book, 1922 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - La Follette's Presidential Candidacy: News clippings re campaign and the relation of the SP to the Conference for Progressive Political Action, 1924 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - SP Convention (New York; Apr 13-17): Partial Minutes and Miscellaneous Documents, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IV:C: The Socialist Party: 1930-1933
    In the years between 1930 and 1933 two groups within the Party organized themselves into loose but identifiable factions: the "Militants," a coalition surrounding Norman Thomas, composed of younger and, in the main, more radical Socialists, and the "Old Guard," a group associated with Morris HilIquit and the New York Socialist establishment. The early stages of the party schism are reflected here in correspondence concerning the dispute between The New Leader and The American Guardian; in a statement by Jack Altman to the "Militant" group in 1933; in letters from Sidney Yellin, Ohio S. P., and Birch Wilson, Pennsylvania SP, concerning disagreements with the National Office, 1933; and in policy statements concerning a proposed united front with the Communist Party. In addition to the factional material, this section includes proposals submitted to the City Convention of New York, 1930; miscellaneous National Convention Papers for 1932; minutes of the National Executive Committee for December 1932; presidential election material, 1932; instructions from the Socialist Speakers Service; and statements, propaganda, and letters of the Continental Congress of Workers and Farmers, 1933.
    - Continental Congress of Workers and Farmers: Statements, propaganda and letters, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Militant Caucus (Jack Altman Statement), 1932 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - N.E.C. Minutes, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - New Leader Issue: Correspondence concerning the dispute between The New Leader and the American Guardian, and Norman Thomas' resignation from The New Leader, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Old Guard Views: Letters from Sidney Yellin, Ohio S.P. and Birch Wilson, Pennsylvania S.P. concerning disagreements with the National Office, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Platforms and Principles, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Proposals (Militant) submitted to the convention of the NYC S.P., 1930 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Reports on Activities, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Socialist Speakers Service Instructions, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - United Front Issue: Policy statements, comments and news clippings., 1933 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IV:D: Young People's Socialist League: 1930-1940
    The Young People's Socialist League (YPSL) material comes from a variety of chapters, although New York City groups are best represented. It includes minutes and reports from groups in Wisconsin, Ohio, Illinois, and New York; miscellaneous National Convention Papers; and some of the minutes and office releases of the National Executive Committee. There are also letters and statements concerning issues of importance to the YPSL: the George Smerkin affair, relations with the Young Communist League, unity with the Social Democratic Federation, and the ultimately consuming problem of world war. Like its parent body, YPSL suffered from factional disputes that are reflected in statements and circulars put out by the "Militants," the "Old Guard," the "Clarity" caucus, and the "Appeal" group. And finally, there are representative periodicals interfiled with the other material in chronological order.
    - Appeal Group, Clarity, Trotskyists, 1937 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Cleveland, 1932-1933 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Committee for Unity, Unity Socialists, 1936 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - May Day Manifesto, 1939 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - National Convention Proceedings, 1933-1935 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - National Convention Proceedings, Resolutions, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - National Convention Proceedings, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - National Convention Proceedings, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - National Executive Committee, 1931-1938 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - New York (N.Y.) Convention Reports, 1934-1937 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - New York Activities, Convention Minutes, Organization Manual, 1930-1938 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Old Guard: National, 1936 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Old Guard: New York, 1933-1935 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Propaganda Material, undated, 1935 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Red Falcons, 1937 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - S.D.F. Unity (Statement), undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - United Front; Young Communist League; Larks-Smerkin Case, 1933-1934 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Wisconsin, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Youth Committee Against War, undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV:E: The Socialist Party: 1934-1935 ("Old Guard" - "Militant" split)
    After 1934 the "Militant" - "Old Guard" conflict became more intense. The National Convention Papers of 1934, particularly the Declaration of Principles adopted at the Convention and the majority and minority reports of the American delegates to the Labor and Socialist International, reveal some aspects of the feud. These are supplemented by letters, statements, and pamphlets from both factions and analyses of the Socialist Party published by other "left wing" groups.
    - Comments of Non-SP Left-Wing Groups on Convention Split in SP, 1934-1935 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Detroit Convention: Agenda; Debates; Resolutions; Report of the American Delegates to the Labor & Socialist International (majority/minority) and resolutions thereon, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Detroit Platform; Declaration of Principles; NYS Resolutions for the Agenda of of the National Convention, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Militant letters, statements, pamphlets, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Militant letters, statements position papers, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - New Leader: Red Vienna Special, Feb 17, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Old Guard, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Old Guard, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Revolutionary Policy Committee; Revolutionary Policy Publishing House, 1934-1936 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Socialist Appeal, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Socialist Party Election Platforms (Bronx, Illinois, Minnesota); Critique of NRA, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV:F: The Socialist Party: 1936 ("Old Guard" - "Militant" split)
    The ""Old Guard" left the Socialist Party to form the Social Democratic Federation in 1936. Letters and statements of the "Militants," the "Old Guard," and the Committee for Unity in the Socialist Party illuminate the parting. For 1936 we also have statements and resolutions on the question of the united front, miscellaneous National Convention Papers, and election propaganda.
    - Altman, Jack: Personal Materials and Letters Concerning His Censure by the California SP, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Convention Minutes, Reports, Resolutions, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Election Propaganda, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Militants: (Includes: Call, Pennsylvania, Racism), 1936 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Organization and Activities (Includes Reports to Convention; Militant Campaign Tactics), 1936 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Party Affairs, 1936-1937 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Socialist Appeal, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Topics on Time / Yar Yochno, Apr 1936 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - United Front, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Subseries IV:G: The Socialist Party: 1937
    The exit of the "Old Guard" did not end factional dispute within the Party. No sooner was the schism accomplished than the "Militants" split into two new factions, the "Old Militants" and the "Clarity" caucus, and shortly thereafter a third group was added, the "Appeal" group, which consisted of former members of the Trotskyist Workers Party who joined the SP en masse toward the end of 1936. Accordingly, 1937 was characterized by internal party feuds, and the letters, statements, and resolutions of the three factions form the bulk of the material. There are also letters and statements concerning the Spanish Civil War, the American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky, and miscellaneous minutes of the National Executive Committee, the National Action Committee, the New York City Executive Committee, and the New York City Central Committee.
    - Appeal Group, Marxist Policy Committee: Letters, Statements and Resolutions re their Expulsion from the SP, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Clarity Group: Letters and Statements re: NYC municipal campaign, relations with the American Labor Party, the SP position on the Appeal group, and the election of delegates to the 1938 convention., 1037 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous: List of union affiliations of New York City SP members, Socialist Handbook, The Socialist Call, October 9, 1937, on the New York City campaign, Newsbulletin of the American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky, Articles on the SP by Howard Bronson, Committee of the Fourth International, Statements of socialists for party unity. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Minutes: National Unemployment Committee, State Executive Committee of Maine, National Executive Committee, National Action Committee, New York City Executive Committee, New York City Central Committee, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Old Militants: Letters and Statements, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Spanish Civil War: Letters and Statements, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IV:H: The Socialist Party: 1938-1939
    The "Appeal" group was expelled from the Socialist Party at the end of 1937, but they did not leave a harmonious party behind them. Letters, statements, and reports concerning the election of delegates to the 1938 National Convention reveal continuing dissension. To some extent this dissension can be attributed to disagreements concerning unity with the Social Democratic Federation, the socialist attitude toward war, and political tactics, in particular the relationship of the SP to the American Labor Party. These disagreements are reflected in letters and notes of the various groups, in the literature of the American Commonwealth Federation and the Keep America Out of War Congress; and in the minutes of the National Executive Committee, the National Action Committee, the National Labor Committee, the State Executive Committee of New York, and the City Central Committee, New York, for 1939, which are included here.
    - American Commonwealth Federation and the Keep America Out of War Congress, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - National Convention: Letters, statements and reports concerning factional disputes in New York City over the election of delegates to the National Convention, 1938 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - National Convention: Reports, Minutes, etc., 1938 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Third Party Question, 1038 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Letters, reports and notes concerning party tactics, the 1939 New York City campaign, relations with theAmerican Labor Party, question of unity with the Social Democratic Federation, union activity, and war (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, Resolutions, Statements: National Executive committee, National Action Committee, National Labor Committee, State Executive Committee, New York, City Central Committee, New York, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IV:I: The Socialist Party and the United Auto Workers, 1937-1941